A Guide to the Papers of Colonel James W. Roberts 1944-1964
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Colonel James W. Roberts
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 2
8 Hollinger Documents Cases
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Provenance
Gift of James W. Roberts, August 1975
Biographical/Historical Information
James Walker Roberts was born on December 2, 1891, in Alexandria, Virginia and was educated at the Friends (High) School in Washington, D.C. Roberts served in the U.S. Army in World War I and attained the rank of Captain in the Field Artillery. He returned to uniform during World War II as a Lt. Colonel commanding a Virginia State Guard Battalion. His service earned Col. Roberts the First Citizen Award of Norfolk Cosmopolitan Club in 1943.
Roberts enjoyed a successful business career in Norfolk which saw him become president and then chairman of the board of the Henry B. Gilprin Co., wholesale drug firm. His political career was equally successful. From 1948-1968 Roberts represented Norfolk in the Virginia General Assembly where he came to occupy a powerful position on the Appropriations Committee. Roberts also served on the Norfolk City Planning Commission and was appointed to several Governor's advisory committees.
Scope and Content Information
Col. Roberts represented Norfolk from 1948 to 1968 in the Virginia House of Delegates. His papers consist principally of legislative correspondence for the period 1963-1964. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically according to its source. In addition there are two boxes of publications issued by agencies of state government and one box of other publications. Also included is the two-volume study, Debates Constitutional Convention 1901-1902 Virginia.
Contents List
- Legislative Study Commission Reports
  - "Reorganization of the Division of Ports," Legislative Study Commission Report 1951 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
- Legislative Correspondence 1963-1964
  Arranged alphabetically by sender.
  - A (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C-Part I (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - C-Part II (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - E (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - F (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - G (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
  - H,I,J-Part I (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
  - H,I,J-Part II (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
  - K,L (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
  - M (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
  - N,O-Part I (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
  - N,O-Part II (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
  - P,Q (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
  - R (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
  - S-Part I (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
  - S-Part II (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
  - T,U,V-Part I (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
  - T,U,V-Part II (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
  - W (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
- Publications
  - Did the Court Interpret or Amend? - A commentary prepared by the Commission on Constitutional Government (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Question and Answer - Citizens Committee for the Hoover Report (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Suggested State Legislation: Program for 1961 - Committee of State Officials on suggested State Legislation of the Council of State Governments (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Corporation Law - issued by the State Corporation Commission (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Tax Laws: A Brief Digest for Taxpayers (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
  - We The States: An Anthology of Historic Documents and Commentaries thereon. Expounding the State and Federal Relationship--issued by the Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Supplement To the Regulations of the Virginia Alcoholic Beverage Control Board (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Opinions of the Attorney General and Report to the Governor of Virginia 1952-1953 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report of the Auditing Committee of the General Assembly 1959 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Election Laws 1960 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report--Virginia Department of Labor and Industry 1963 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Motor Vehicle Laws of Virginia 1952 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Manual on the Planning and Execution of State Capital Outlays 1944 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Speakers and Clerks of the Virginia House of Delegates 1776-1955 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report of the Superintendent of Public Instruction 1951-1952 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report of the State Corporation Commission--Appendix I 1948 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Traffic Crash Facts 1959 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Department of Conservation and Development - The Board of Directors, The Director, Commissioners and Division Programs 1956 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Treasurer of Virginia 1956 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Retirement Plan For Public Employees 1960 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Welfare Bulletin June 1953 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Debates Constitutional Convention 1901-1902 Virginia, Vol. I (Box Box 7)
  - Debates Constitutional Convention 1901-1902 Virginia, Vol. II (Box Box 8)